This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Kolide sends employees important,
timely, and relevant security
recommendations for their Linux, Mac,
and Windows devices right inside Slack.
Kolide is perfect for organizations that
want to move beyond a traditional
lockdown model to one where employees
are educated about security and device
management while they're fixing
important problems.
Visit kolide.com/seradio
to sign up today.
That's k o l i d e dot com slash s e
radio.
Enter your email when prompted to
receive your free Kolide gift bundle
after trial activation.
You can try Kolide with all its features
on an unlimited number of devices for
free for 14 days. No credit card
required.
Try it out at kolide.com/seradio.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host Gavin Henry and today my
guest is Robert Seacord.
Robert Seacord is a technical director
at NCC Group where he develops and
delivers secure coding training in C and
C++ and other languages.
Seacord is an expert on the C standards
committee.
His six previous books include the CERT
C Coding Standard and Secure Coding in C
and C++.
Robert, welcome to Software Engineering
Radio. Is there anything I missed in
your bio that you'd like to add? No,
that was quite complete. Thanks for
having me here.
A pleasure. So, I'd like to start off
with a brief history of the C language
and then touch on why programming in C
can be insecure.
We're going to
also then move on to the sort top five
security issues and then the last bit of
the show going to be talking on various
ways and tools we can use to help us
write secure C programs.
Okay?
Small disclosure, I might mention an
open source project I'm working on
called Centrifuge, which is written in C
for various things that
has come up while while I've been
writing the code and tools that I found
security issues that I
went through
and thought that weren't an issue and
things I found in
in your books in the section
on on how to
improve your code. So, I think it'll be
a nice bit.
Sure.
So, let's lay down some foundations.
When was C created?
Okay, so
I had to look this up because I'm
actually not quite that old, but it
first appeared in 1972
and it was developed by Dennis Ritchie
at Bell Laboratories
in New Jersey.
Yeah, so it's had a very long history.
It was It was based on a typeless
language called B, as you might imagine,
cuz programmers aren't never been very
good at naming things.
Cool. And
are there such a thing as versions or
how does that work?
Yeah, well, yeah, there's there's a lot
of there's a lot of variation in what we
call C, right? So, there was K&R C,
which was the Cunningham Ritchie kind of
corresponded to the to their book back
in the '70s.
And back in the '70s ANSI started a
committee to standardize the language.
They published their first standard in
1989, so that's often referred to as
C89.
And the next year that was published by
ISO, so that was fast-tracked to the
the International Standards
Organization, C90. And a lot of people
have assured me, including John Benita,
who was the previous convener of the C
Standards Committee, that those two
standards are exactly the same. There's
just a different cover page. But it's
actually quite hard to define copies of
those original standards, but a lot of
embedded code is still written to C89
C90.
And then there's been several versions,
major versions of the standard released
since then. So the next one was C99
and C99, you know, was a little kind of
slow on adoption, but you know, it added
a bunch of of features. C11 was the
first standard that I I worked on from
beginning to end.
And C11 primarily
introduced parallel programming,
concurrent programming, threads, thread
library, atomics. And it was it was
meant to also address security. I I'm
not sure it did as good a job of
addressing security as it did
addressing, you know, parallel
execution, but
we did add things like Annex K, you
know, which is the bound checking
interface or the the underbar S
functions. Many people think underbar S
stands for, you know, security, but it
actually stands for bounds controlled
interface.
And we added that we added Annex L,
which was the
analyzability annex, and you know, made
some some other small improvements here
and there to address security. That was
C11.
That was 2011, isn't it?
Yeah, 2011. We just we just have the
single digits. I mean, I guess
eventually
we'll we'll wrap around, but I I hope to
be dead by then and expect it to be
someone else's problem.
You mentioned ANSI. That's the American
Yeah, that's American ANSI. And then
nowadays it's it's it's institute, isn't
it?
American National Standards Institute.
Okay, yeah.
But nowadays it's actually there's a
group called Insights, which is sort of
under the umbrella of of ANSI. And so,
if you're in the US, you're a member of
the Insights committee.
And you know, Insights gets a single
vote in in ISO. So, ISO's an
international standards body, so it's
one one nation one vote at at ISO. And
the committee's actually it's very it's
very US-centric. We had a meeting some
years ago in Delft in the Netherlands,
and there's a portion of the meeting
where we we just handle Insights
business. So, we ask people who aren't
part of the US body to to leave. And the
only person to leave was the host of the
meeting. And and this was a meeting
taking place in Europe. There was only
one European there, and it was the
was the
was the host. So, so usually we get
better participation from
Northern Europe, Canada, but not not
much beyond there. Hasn't been a lot of
participation from
Asia or or elsewhere lately. And is that
because C's not used there, or
they don't participate?
Well, it might be used there, but it's
it's you know, all the compiler vendors
are in the US primarily. There's you
know, IBM, their compiler group is in
Markham in Canada. And so, so that's
actually the Canadian representation is
from from IBM. A well-known Canadian
company, of course.
And um
so
there's not really versions, it's a
standard, and and that changes each
Yeah, well, there's versions of the
standard, and that that sort of drives
the baseline. So, you know, there's C11,
there's C17.
C17, some people mistakenly call it C18
cuz it was published by ISO in in 2018,
but
it's actually it is actually is a 2017
standard. And and that that was really
that was an one. It was just really bug
fixes of C11.
So so no one really should be using C11.
C11's like C17 with bugs and C17 is C11
without bugs.
But there's, you know, of course all the
compiler vendors are fix all the bugs in
C11. So you you you won't see them
anymore regardless of which which
standard you specify.
And so C17's the current version.
And we are currently working on C23.
And the deadline for papers to introduce
new features has come and gone as of
this past
I think it was November as of November.
And so
so we know we know what's not going to
be in C23 right now, which is anything
we haven't got a paper on. And what's
going to be in it is still up in the air
cuz we have to see if we can get
consensus on, you know, the remaining
the remaining proposals that are in
front of the committee.
And that's what
ends up that in the compiler, doesn't
it? What the version or standard the
compiler supports? Well, it it could,
right? So so you know, well so first of
all, when when when we create the
standard in C
there's a strong requirement for
existing implementations, right? So so
the C committee more than most
committees does not like to invent
things, you know, so
we like to find things that are
being used in practice that could
benefit from standardization because
that might increase portability over a
number of platforms.
And then, you know, get it get it into
the standard. And and and you know,
sometimes the committee will I'll use
the term make improvements to the
existing practice. They do like to to
fiddle. And and that's that's good and
bad. I mean, it's nice to to maybe make
some improvements, but at the same time,
you know, now it's not exactly exist
existing practice anymore, right? Now
you made some changes to it. And some
things like, you know, Annex K,
you know, the committee fiddled with
that a bit and got to the point where
the existing implementation from
Microsoft became non-conforming to the
standard and they weren't really up for
changing it.
And and so, yeah, so the standard,
you know, I'm trying to find a different
word than the standard, you know, it's
that's a standard, right?
No, but you touched on a good point
there that
the standard is there to reinforce
portability, I think, that's what you're
trying to get to.
Yeah.
But all these compilers, you know, they
they're they're they're always each each
implementation, right? Each compiler
implementation in a, you know, exist
over continuum, right? So, you'll have a
compiler that has say maybe it's fully
implemented C99,
but they're they're working towards
implementing all the C11 or C17
features, right? And so, it's somewhere
in between and then, you know, most
compilers have compiler-specific
extensions that you can use, right?
Which are not standardized. And so,
so every every implementation, there's a
lot of
there's a lot of variation, you know,
each each sort of standard version is is
is sort of a different flavor of the
language. And then the actual compiler
implementations, they'll, you know,
they'll fall into different areas in
terms of which standards they implement
and which additional features. And so,
so there's there's a
there's a consistent sort of portable,
you know, backbone, but there's there's
a certain amount of, you know, variation
kind of built on top of that.
Yeah, just touching on the bit where you
spoke about it's really C17 and not C18.
In my open source project that I
mentioned
when I was getting the
the continuous integration test setup as
it were to to actually build my project
with the uh compiler flags I put on
it was GCC standard C18 cuz I'm running
Fedora Linux latest for my desktop I
develop on
but the runners where this code was
built on GitHub was Ubuntu 20 LTS and
they didn't have that flag support in
those GCCs.
I think it was there or when I was
testing on NetBSD and OpenBSD they
didn't, they only supported C11. So,
even things not even that many years old
they haven't caught up or it's just the
version of compiler that was released
with that operating system. So,
I understand what you mean by depending
on how the compilers are implemented and
who's rolled them out.
Right.
Yeah, and and you know, Microsoft is is
always been an interesting case because
they
you know, they've always been sort of
comfortable partially supporting
standards. So, you know, supporting
parts of standards they like but
ignoring parts they don't.
And But that's not a standard, is it?
You either do it all or you don't.
Yeah. Yeah.
That's true. So, for a long time they
didn't like all the parts of C99 and
they they just kind of took a pass on
those bits. But they're they've sort of
announced a direction where they want to
sort of become more aligned with the
you know, with the C standard. They're
not really they haven't been sending
anyone to to the committee meetings so
it's hard to tell, you know, exactly
what their
future relationship with the language is
but
you know, compilers like Clang and and
GCC do do a very good job kind of
keeping up with the
latest version of the standards, and you
can you know, you can get some even C23
kind of features supported in those
compilers as well.
Excellent. Well, I'm going to move us on
to the next section of the show. Mhm.
Which is really about
the top five security issues that I've
come up with a bit of research, and I
want you to correct me on them. So,
before we dig into these five, if we
could spend a minute or two
to understand why a C program can be
insecure, and then we'll dig into a
into the five
issues that
I've listed.
Well, yeah. So, so, you know, all all
programming languages are insecure, and
you know, they're all general-purpose
programming languages. So, they they all
can sort of achieve the same things,
right? So, they have the same
you know, the they're all Turing
complete, right? And they've got
different abstractions, different idioms
for programming in those languages.
But, you know, in the way languages are
broken, they're
they can be quite different, right?
Because that's
that's not an intentional design, that's
sort of the defect surface of the
language, or however you want to
describe it. And and and so,
you know, if you look at a language like
Java,
you know, which had been billed as a
secure language for for many years, it's
got some some serious problems with
things like deserialization,
which is basically allows an attacker to
execute their own code inside your
virtual machine, right? So, the
the level of
It's a very topical language at the
moment, isn't it? With
Yeah.
Everything that's been been going on in
the past two weeks. We have to be
careful of timelines on this
type of live show, but the big one with
Log4j,
poor open source guys.
Right. Yeah. And I mean that's I haven't
studied that carefully. I mean that
mostly seems like a design flaw. I mean
that they
It's kind of like you said where
code can be injected and it runs where
it shouldn't be. Right. Yeah.
So So yeah, so Java is, you know, got a
pretty significant attack surface and
and it's at a it's at a certain level
where,
you know, it it sort of
in in the libraries and in the features
and ways that those features can be sort
of misused to exploit the the code. C
being sort of a simpler compiled
language, you know, doesn't have that
attack surface, but
C and C++ are sort of well-known for for
memory safety issues. And these are
things where
basically you
you read or write outside the bounds of
an object. And C and C++, you know,
these languages are designed optimally
efficient. So
they sort of trust the programmer is not
going to make these type mistakes and it
turns out that trust had been, you know,
very misplaced cuz programmers make
these mistakes all the time. And you
know, if you write outside the bounds of
an object, that can have various
consequences. It's undefined behavior,
but, you know, depending on what that
write does. And and so, you know, it
could overwrite data, it could
overwrite, you know, function pointers.
It could overwrite the return address on
the stack. And, you know, attackers can
exploit that that kind of problem by,
you know, among other things, you know,
injecting code into your into your
process and overwriting the return
address on the stack with the
the address of that malicious code. So
when a function goes return, instead of
return to the caller, it executes, you
know, code that's been injected by the
attacker.
And then that code runs with the
permissions of the vulnerable process.
So, so that's that's a pretty
significant style of attack.
Okay, well, that's that's a good
overview of a few things that may be
insecure.
Let me break down some of them. And
before we start on this next bit,
when we're talking about C and you
mentioned the word object, which always
makes me think of
an object-oriented program, like a
JavaScript object or a Java one. What do
we mean in C when we talk about an
object? Yeah, I didn't know this was
going to be a
really deeply technical. Well, as simple
as you can make it, just a
just to put a
a single sentence definition on an
object. Yeah, we have a memory
management study group that's trying to
answer that question. So, Oh, maybe we
can't do a simple answer then.
But basically, an object is Okay, I
mean, so you have you have in C, you
have functions and you have objects,
right? So, an object is everything
that's not a function. So, that's a a
variable would be an object or you know,
you can have an object in dynamically
allocated storage. So, yeah, it's
basically uh
That is correct. Well, that's exactly
what I was just going to read from your
book. So, in your book, Effective C,
you say an object is storage in which
you can represent values. To be precise,
an object is defined by the C standard
as a region of data storage in the
execution environment, the contents of
which can be represent and which can
represent values.
The added note, when referencing object
can be interpretated as having a
particular type.
So, yeah, that is
a big tick for that answer. Thank you.
Oh, thanks. Glad I I'm glad I'm
consistent.
So, yeah, you touched on a couple of
things that I was going to pull apart
shortly.
And that's to do with how
these memory issues are actually
exploited. We'll We'll start off on my
list.
So,
do my own project and other things like
that, whenever I
save something or I'm working on an IDE
and I push it to GitHub, I've got all
sorts of static analysis on it that
we'll mention in the next section,
but it usually comes back with something
like
a string issue.
So,
I've always understood strings to be a
security issue as in
not null-terminated or an array of
characters. People treating that as a
string when it's not a string. Could you
give us some information on why a string
can be
insecure?
Yeah, strings are kind of rough. You
know, so so strings are they're not a
they're not a primitive type in either C
or C++. And so,
they're they're they're constructed on
top of arrays. And in C arrays are
are problematic in and of themselves,
right? And so, you know, for starters,
we know that, you know, there's no
there's no implicit bounds checking, you
know, and and there's a lot of
functions,
you know, such as such as strcpy where
you're copying a string from from a
source to a destination and it's going
to copy the entire length of the string,
but there's no indication in that
function of of the size, say, of the
destination array. And so,
uh strcpy will just do what you ask it
to do, which is copy from,
you know, this source to this
destination without
checking to see if there's room for that
to make that copy string inside the
bounds of that destination object. And
so, the the problem with the arrays, one
of the problems with arrays when you
pass them to a function, uh they decay
to a pointer to the first element of the
array. And so, once you're inside the
function,
there is no way to determine the size of
the entire array. So, that size
information has to be passed to be
available. So, so functions like strcpy
that don't pass the size, you know, that
the the the library functions trusting
you the programmer to,
you know, pass it an object which will
fit into the destination array. And if
it doesn't, you'll have, you know, this
undefined behavior
and, you know, this potentially
vulnerable code.
And
when the
So, I always remember that
the name of an array is also a pointer.
So, when you pass it into a function
that, like you said, it decays to just a
pointer.
You You can still
find out what type of pointer that is
inside your function.
So, you know, is that correct?
Well, I mean, the the type of the point
is the pointer's typed, you know, so I
mean, you could have void pointers in C,
but that's not
particularly a great idea. So,
typically, a string would be a a char
pointer. I mean, typically, I mean,
correctly, it would be a char pointer.
So,
yeah, but
you don't know how long that is and you
don't you have to give it
Yeah, yeah, you don't know how long it
is. And and even even, you know, the
idea that it's an array is
not necessarily the case, right? It
could just be a pointer to a single
character.
So,
you have to think about
cuz what code I've seen where
they pass in the length, they usually
use
one of the standard functions, string
length,
but again, that function has to figure
out how long your string is.
So, do you have to take an extra step
and make sure it's got a a null is null
terminated?
Or do you have to is there something
that we can reach to so we don't have to
think about any of this with strings?
What
do you recommend?
So So there's again, there's no like
string type, right? There's no primitive
string type, so it's an array, and the
definition of a string is that basically
there's a null character before the
bound, right? So, if there is no no no
no character before the bound, it's not
actually string. It's a character array,
right?
And that's okay, right? It's okay to
have a character array in C. It's
defined behavior, but the it becomes
undefined behavior if you pass a
character array to a strlen function,
right? Because it's going to
you know, it's going to examine each
element of that character array for a
null character, and it's going to
continue looking for a null character
until it finds one.
So, if strlen, which again doesn't take
a size, it doesn't know what size the
string is that it's examining, if it
doesn't find a null character before the
bound, it's going to continue to look
for through memory for a null character,
and as soon as it
as soon as that function accesses
storage beyond the bound of the array,
it's now undefined behavior, right? And
once you have undefined behavior in your
code, all bets are off, right? That that
that program can now exhibit any type of
behavior. So,
So, yeah, there's certainly a
requirement to ensure
that any any string you pass to a string
function is actually string, meaning
that it has a
it has a null termination before the
bound.
Yeah, I've seen some of the
documentation on
some of the string functions that
look to
work around this by say then they say,
"If there's no a null character found at
that length that you passed then we'll
make sure there's one there." sort of
thing.
Right. A lot of functions, newer, sort
of more secure functions will
ensure that when they create a string,
that it will it will be properly
null-terminated. If you if you perhaps,
yeah, give it more data than it has room
to store in in whatever sized object you
have, then it will, you know, overwrite
the little the last character it's
trying to store with a null character.
So, you've got to properly
null-terminate a string.
And so, you know, I mean, this choice of
a data type was made early on, and
could very well be the wrong
data type. I mean, you know, maybe
having a size, you know, followed by
the string and not using a null
termination, maybe that would have been
a
a better, you know, more efficient, more
secure design, but it's it's
it's not something that's likely to
change at this point in the in the
evolution of these languages.
And I think if we move on to number two
on my list now, I think we've touched a
little bit on it. And I've called this
buffer overruns and underruns.
Mhm. And I think you've helped me
understand the question I was going to
ask in the section
where in my project, essentially peer
one, I've got some errors on my IDE
where I'm doing a
I think it's a string
and compare. So, I'm basically checking
a URL that comes in to see if it
matches.
Send the data to one of my functions.
So, I've got the the URL, and I've got
how
the size of how long I want to look
along the
the array of
chars to find a match, basically.
So, I've given it a max path length. I
think it's of
1,024 or something.
But my ID says I shouldn't check that
URL string
longer than the strings there.
Even though it finds a match and my
tests all work, cuz I think that's just
what you've explained there. What once
it gets past the char of
the array of chars, which might not be a
string, i.e. it's not null-terminated,
all bets are off because it's undefined
behavior when it gets to say
char 101 of the the URL that's 100 chars
long.
Right. Right. Yeah, you definitely can't
examine characters beyond the bounds of
that object
beyond the bounds of that character
array.
Yeah, so I think when the URL comes in,
you need to do a a size check on it and
then make sure you're not checking past
that for a match. Would be the correct
way.
Yeah. I mean, so you've got you've got a
max path buffer, right, that you're
storing it in. So so you've got that
amount of room for that array, but
you're comparing it to
you know, another another string. And so
right, you don't want to
to exceed the bounds of either, you
know, either of those Yeah, it's
actually a the string and compare. So
I've got the URL
on the on the
the length of the the string that I want
to compare against. So like {forward
slash} home, I want to make sure that
goes to the right place,
or about or something like that, about
page. And I've got a max length, so it
it's going along that string for as long
as I passed length for, and it says
that's bad, but
you don't know how long the path is
until you've calculated the path. So
you're kind of getting this like chicken
and egg type situation. Mhm. But yeah,
so
when we talk about going past the end of
array, that would be an overrun, is it a
buffer overrun?
Or is that an underrun?
Well, yeah. So so so there's these terms
that get kicked around in security like
buffer overflow and buffer under-run and
overrun. And I don't know what any of
those words mean. I mean, they're
they're they're they're very kind of
loosely used terms in security, but they
don't have very precise definitions, you
know, so in in in the C language, really
we just talk about an access outside the
bounds of an object and and we don't we
don't care about what that access looks
like, right? So, you could have
you could start at the beginning of an
array and you can increment, you know, a
pointer or an index and then, you know,
run off the the end of the array, right?
And that's that's an out-of-bounds
access. You might call that a buffer
overflow. And then,
you know, you could start at the end of
an array and you could decrement the
pointer and then you can run off
that end of the memory. Sometimes you'll
just sort of arbitrarily jump from you
might have a some sort of integer error
and jump from accessing an array to some
random place in memory. And and again,
it's I don't know what that's called, is
that a buffer overflow or buffer
overrun, but it's just it's definitely
an access outside the bounds of that
object, which is
you know, undefined behavior. You can't
you can't take a you you you can take a
pointer to an array
and you can add or subtract an integer
value to it as long as the
pointer still refers to the same array
or to one past that array, the two far
element. But, if if the if the if the
pointer you formed from that pointer
arithmetic is outside of that bound,
it's just undefined behavior and
you know, what you call it, you know,
kind of varies. There's, you know, it's
it's a little bit unrelated, but
people like to talk about
integer overflow and integer underflow
in C, but there's actually no such thing
as integer underflow. That's That's just
someone's creation.
You know, every If if you if you have an
operation integer operation that forms a
value that can't be represented, that's
integer overflow. There's there is no
such thing as integer underflow, but
people like to use that term for
whatever reason.
That's a good explanation. Thank you.
So, sure.
So, we've done something here where
we've gone outside the bounds of what
we're trying to do.
My The third thing on my list is is mem
what I've called memory leaks.
So, when you request some memory from
the operating system with one of the
allocation functions,
and
you don't free it.
So,
you get what I think is called a run
time leak run time leak or a corrupt
corrupt memory. So,
run time would be where you're
continually asking for this memory,
but you're not freeing it. So, you're
using more than you should be. Is that a
correct definition?
Yeah, so there there was a lot of stuff
that was slightly wrong in that
question.
Good. That's what I wanted to hear.
Correct me.
Yeah. So, so for starters, you know,
there there's memory allocation
function, right? malloc, calloc,
realloc, aligned alloc, right? And none
of these
directly request memory from the
operating system, right? So, so the
process has a has a memory allocator
that runs as part of the same process
space, right? And so, your your memory
allocator will
request a very large block of memory
from the operating system, and then it
will manage that. And so, when you make
a call to malloc, it's allocating, you
know, storage it's allocating a piece of
storage from this large block of memory
that the the memory manager's managing
within the within the process, right?
Is that part of the kernel that's doing
this memory management? No, it's all in
your process.
So, you know, the the the memory
management, you know,
you're going to link to a library, and
that library has implementations of stir
copy and malloc, and all these functions
run as part of your executable, right?
In your your process. So, this isn't
like a memory pool that I've created.
This is something to do with how a an
executable is created.
Well, yeah. So, so I mean, when you
when you start up, the memory manager is
going to it is going to go to the
operating system. It's going to get a a
block of memory, right? But then, once
it gets this large block, which is
basically the heap, right?
It's going to your memory manager is now
going to manage that heap storage for
you, right? So,
when you make a request to malloc,
that's going to
execute the malloc function, which is
part of this, you know, memory manager
implementation.
And it's going to say, you know, what's
the next available number of, you know,
next available block of memory that's at
least this number of bytes large, and
carve that off this bigger block, and
return that to
the user. So,
that entire process doesn't doesn't
involve the kernel at that point, right?
That block's been carved out. The only
time the kernel might become involved
again is if if you completely use all
the allocated memory from the operating
system, you might then seek to sort of
extend that, but that's
that's one implementation. Doesn't
necessarily I mean, the other
possibility is that at that point, that
allocation would fail for for inadequate
memory.
Okay. And so, when we're talking about
these
out of bounds
things that happen. I'm not going to use
the word overrun or underrun again.
Does it make a difference if it's
over does something that our balance
into memory that we haven't freed or
are we contained within what the memory
allocation tool has given us for memory?
Or is it just undefined? You know, is
there a difference between
say we've corrupt some of our own memory
or not freed it and then one of these
array operations we're doing
ends up trying to go into that. It's
just undefined or
What I'm actually trying to ask is
when you see exploits of these types of
things
and they are
they know that we're not
cleaning up memory or there's some type
of
bit of memory they can get to with this
exploit to run their own code.
Yeah, how do how do they predictably get
at that if these things are all quite
undefined and and random, you know?
Yeah, well, undefined,
you know,
is a term used by the standard, right?
So, so the standard says
simply we we haven't defined what
happens here, right? And so, a
particular implementation, of course, is
going to do something, right? And and
because it's not defined by the standard
what it does, you as a programmer don't
really know what it does, right? So, so
sometimes, you know, the implementation
sort of aligns with your, you know, your
expectations of programmer what sort of
behavior you're going to get, in which
case you could have
code you could have executables
generated from code containing undefined
behavior, which is actually correct, but
more commonly,
you know, if you're invoking undefined
behavior, that suggests that you, you
know, you don't have a correct
understanding of
of the language with regards to that
behavior and most likely the code is is
wrong.
Now, now when we talk about memory, uh
heat memory,
there's, you know, several classes of
potential
potential errors which can lead to
vulnerabilities.
The first one, which we've kind of
discussed already, is buffer overflows,
right? So, buffer overflows can occur in
any uh memory segment. So, they can
occur in in the stack, the in the data
segment, or in the heap. And the
consequences, you know, so so an
overflow in the heap,
in you know, anytime you write outside
the bounds of an object, it's undefined
behavior. Can you define the stack and
the heap briefly? Just in context.
Yeah. So, so the stack and the heap, I
mean, I'll I'll say I'll start out by
saying that neither concept is defined
in the C standard, right? So, so these
are these are kind of like
implementation concepts, but typically a
stack
is, you know, a data structure which
supports program execution by allowing
you to, you know, have a function that
calls another function, and then, you
know, creates a stack frame for a
function that it's calling, where it
preserves all the local variables and
arguments that are being passed to that
function and so forth. And then that
function could call another function,
and that function could recurse, right?
So, you could wind up with multiple
instances
of a of the same function on the stack.
And then, once the function returns, the
stack sort of unwinds, right? So, you
return back to the calling function and
reestablish that function stack frame,
so it has access to the local variables.
And so, the stack is, you know, the
execution stack is is a data structure
to allow for this basically, you know,
functional style of of programming. So,
that's a stack. And, you know, a typical
variable that you would declare inside
of a function, a non-static variable. If
you just have a function F and you say
int I,
that variable is an automatic variable
that's declared
in the scope of that function. And what
happens is when when you call that
function, a stack frame gets created for
that function and instances of that
variable gets allocated on the stack,
right? And so, once that function
returns, the lifetime of that that
variable ends and it can no longer be
accessed.
So, so
you've got two other data segments. You
have you have, you know, the the data
segment, which is where static variables
go. And And static variables, global
variables are
you know, they're they have the life
same lifetime as that of the program,
right? So, they're they're always
accessible and that's where you, you
know,
you might keep a counter or something,
right? Where a function will come, you
know, you'll call a function, you'll
you'll increment this counter. The
function will exit, but the count will
still remain because it's a global
variable.
And global variables have their uses and
they have their problems, you know.
But the the next type of the next
segment is the heap.
And the heap is
where, you know, where dynamically
allocated storage is exist and
you know, the heap is
you know, allows you to to allocate
storage as you need it during program
execution. And those objects persist
until they're explicitly
deallocated or destroyed, right? So,
so those have a, you know, those have a
their own kind of lifetime that's based
on you, you know, allocating and
deallocating.
So,
where the where leaks could happen.
Memory could get corrupt. Yeah. So, so
So, there's the buffer overflows on the
heap and and those
are exploitable depend you know, and how
they're exploited depends on
the implementation of the, you know, of
your memory manager. So, some memory
managers implement the Knuth algorithm
which uses these boundary tags where
you'll have control structures before
and after each allocated block. So, if
you write beyond
the bounds of the allocated object,
you'll start overriding these control
structures in the heap, corrupting the
heap, and you, you know, an attacker
could override those structures
basically again to arbitrary text you
write arbitrary code.
And the specifics of that depend on the
the implementation of the allocator, but
there's also
two other classes of problems and well,
at least two other classes problems with
memory, allocated memory. So, one is
you allocate memory and then you fail to
to deallocate, to release it. That's a
memory leak and you know, a memory leak
can be benign if you
if you have a short-running program and
you don't ever exhaust memory, but if
you have something like a server
that's going to run for extended period
of time,
you know, as it runs, if it's
continually leaking memory, that memory
is no longer available to the, you know,
the memory allocator to allocate to the
process. So, eventually that system is
going to exhaust memory and
that type of defect, you know, once that
happens,
your server's not going to
be very effective at
serving, you know, because it's it's
going to start having memory failures
and constantly be in a state of trying
to recover from from memory errors.
And so, that that situation is is sort
of known as, you know, resource
exhaustion and one form of attack is,
you know, denial of service attack by
resource exhaustion, right? Where where
an attacker,
you know, finds a memory leak in your
system, exploits that to exhaust your
memory, and now
it appears that your server's
operational, but actually it's it's no
longer serving requests because it it
it's out of memory and it can't function
properly, right? So so out of memory
fail fail failing to properly deallocate
storage when it's no longer required can
lead to those sort of denial of service
attacks. The other problem is
you can
accidentally
release the same storage multiple times,
right? And that's often referred to as a
double free vulnerability. Double free
vulnerability is
it's it looks a little bit different,
but it can have the same consequence as
a buffer overflow on the heap, which is
that an attacker could exploit that to
execute arbitrary code. So double free
is is also quite dangerous sort of
coding error. Would you be able to give
them an example of I know it's hard
because it depends on the program and
implementation of where it's running and
things as far as I understand it, but
how can an attacker
exploit what you've just explained with
the double free or a
you know, or an overrun or underrun? How
do they get this code? Is it assembly
language that they put in the code and
they inject that into this memory of
area um area of memory or what does that
look like?
Yeah. Well, so
you know, if we just discuss just sort
of a basic exploit.
Yeah, like printing your name or
something. I don't know. Something
really easy to kind of follow.
yeah, in independent of the error rate.
I mean, so what typi- what can happen is
an attacker can, you know, yeah, can
inject, you know, executable
instructions into your process memory.
And it can really do that on any input
operation. And and, you know, there's
valid, you know, there's executable code
that looks like valid ASCII. There's
executable code that looks like valid,
you know, UTF-8 strings. So, you know,
whatever type of string you're
inputting,
it it I mean, it's always a good idea to
validate that string to the extent
possible, but sometimes you just can't.
Sometimes it's just kind of, you know,
a string data. I mean, and and so
you've got a really good section in your
effective C book on validating the
program arguments on the command line.
Yeah, yeah. I thought that was pretty
extensive. Oh, thanks. And and uh I
mean, secure coding in C and C++ really
goes into,
you you know, these exploits more. The
effective C book was is meant more of a
introductory text. So, I don't try to go
too into depth in, you know, how how
exploits, you know, are you know, how
how to write exploits, but
you know, I I'm I I I try to write that
book to you provide kind of a strong
foundation to programmers. So, I think
that's why I like it so much.
Yeah, well, thank you. I mean, in a way,
you know, if you
if you code correctly and you avoid
undefined behaviors, right, you don't
your code is secure. You don't need to
understand how it might be exploited.
That that, you know, the study of sort
of how code is exploited is is really
motivational. It's It's for people who
like, "Oh, I've got you know, legacy
code base with tens of thousands of
errors, right? So, how do I prioritize
that?" And so, you know, you you you
kind of talk about,
you know, what the various errors are,
how they can be exploited, how
how you might mitigate against these
problems with, you know, sometimes sort
of runtime strategies, which would
protect against, you know, exploits of
of all of these and and then also about,
you know, secure coding practices, how
to correctly the code so it's not
exploitable. But getting getting a
legacy system,
you know, poorly written legacy system
to be secure, you know, can be a
significant investment in, you know,
rewriting it and improving the code.
Yeah, I think you've touched nicely onto
number four which is
on my list which is inputs. So,
I've got some questions to do with
processing command line arguments,
environmental variables,
defensive programming, how network
traffic is processed at runtime into
data structures, things like that. But I
think
just really understanding listening to
what you've explained with them the
memory leaks and attack vectors,
it just depends on how the input is
coming into your program and that you
you process it correctly.
That could be the how it's You know,
when you see the CVE exploit list
and it says, you know, there's a double
free or a buffer overflow or something,
in certain situations doing this, you
know, if the wind's blowing northwest
and you're wearing your favorite jumper,
this might get exploited type thing. It
just depends on how it's coming into
that program and what the program does.
Is that a fair summary?
Yeah, it's, you know,
some of it's quite tricky, right? I
mean, so so you'll look at some source
code and it it will have, you know, it
has some undefined behavior and
it might be, you know, on on this
platform, under these circumstances with
whatever runtime protections are
available, that this
this particular coding error won't be
exploitable, right? But you could run
that on you could port that to a
different system, you could run on
different platform, you could change
something about the runtime environment,
or you know, you could upgrade your
compiler where the compiler's now, you
know, used to do one thing with an
undefined behavior, but now it's now
they've developed an optimization that
takes advantage of that undefined
behavior to improve your performance.
And now, you know, a problem which was
in you know, the error was always
present in the source code, but now
because of this new optimization
that that that executable has been
changed and it's now, you know, now is
vulnerable to to to attack. So,
sometimes, you know, many times it's
easier to repair the code than it is to
understand all the potential security
consequences of
uh of an exploit. You know, so so in
cases where it's it's cheap to fix,
usually just makes sense to fix it. I
mean, there's some cases where, you
know, if you put some code on the you
know, the the Mars rover and you you
know, you you land it on Mars, right?
It's it's a bit more involved to repair
that code, right? So, you want to you
want to analyze that defect more. You
want to analyze that vulnerability more
to find out whether it's, you know, how
much of a security risk is is it worth
repairing or not. But many cases, it's
just easier to
to make the repair to the source code
cuz if the undefined behaviors
eliminated, you you shouldn't have you
shouldn't have a vulnerability in most
cases. Now now there are
there are vulnerabilities which
can exist absent of undefined behavior.
You know, these these can be logical
errors or, you know, just simply things
like a memory leak, right? So, if your
program accidentally, you know, prints
out or logs,
you know, some some you know, personally
identify personally identifiable
information. It doesn't necessarily have
to have undefined behavior to do that,
right? So, you you could have a you
could have a you know, I almost want to
use the phrase insecure by design, Yeah,
which has nothing to do with C. That's
just the engineering software
engineering. That's nothing to worry
about that.
Right.
Okay, I think that was a
a good summary. And so, with a say an
improved compiler,
could that catch a double free if it's
tracking
the number of times you freed something
or is that what a garbage collection
system would do?
Oh, yeah. Well, C doesn't really have
garbage collection. So, Yeah, no, I was
just that was just an example.
Yeah. Yeah. So, so, you know, double
free, those type of errors, there are
ways to catch it, right? So, so one one
one mechanism is just to, you know, so
so compiler does some analysis, right?
It doesn't do a lot of analysis. So,
there's there's static analysis tools
that do more depth more in-depth
analysis
Yeah, that's what I'm going to touch on
in the next section. Yeah, yeah. I've
really enjoyed this middle section. So,
I'd better move us on cuz we're a little
bit over our time on this bit. So, just
the last thing I have in my list cuz I
think we've done a really good job and
I didn't say it at the time, but I
really enjoyed the our description of
the stack and the heap. That made
everything really clear.
Cool. So, my last point is
Sorry, that was a bad pun. It's dangling
pointers. Mm. What are these and what
problems do they cause? Just a minute or
two and then we'll move on to
the tools to help you
be a better programmer. Well, well, they
certainly cause bad puns, but you know,
the problem with a dangling pointer is
that, you know, it could lead kind of
directly to two classes of exploitable
defects, right? One being double free,
which we've just discussed, right? So,
if you free a pointer and you don't
assign it to null, you could
free that pointer second time and we've
already discussed that that can be
vulnerable. If you do set it to null and
you free a null pointer, that's a no-op.
So, that has no
no effect on the code. The other problem
with a dangling pointer is that it's now
it's now pointing to memory which has
been
deallocated, possibly deallocated and
then reallocated. So, so writing to that
pointer is now undefined behavior. And
say for say that storage is deallocated,
you write to it, you know, once you once
you deallocate storage, the the memory
manager takes it over and it might use
the kind of user space to insert control
structures in order to track keep track
of free blocks of storage. So, if you
write to these dangling pointers again,
you could overwrite these control
structures corrupting the heap and
potentially doing that in a way which
again possible to to execute arbitrary
code.
Yeah, I've seen that in a lot in
something I do in in my codes and
in Yiannis Good stats book who I had on
the show and who you know cuz you work
with him in standards episode 414
and also a shoutout to your article for
the IEEE secure coding in C and C++.
and strings and integers and your other
article on effective C.
I've got those links in the show notes
but all his and I think in your code
examples
after a free, the pointer is set to zero
which is the null. Hm. And this as well.
Excellent. So, that was a really good
coverage. So, in the last section
I don't have as much time as as I hoped
but
we've done a good job on
some crossovers here.
So, we've got
IDs and things that we use as we're
writing the code that try and give us as
much help as possible.
We've got our sort of build tools. But
you mentioned earlier
static and
dynamic analysis. I think you mentioned
dynamic analysis, but I'll mention it
here anyway.
So, what's static and and dynamic
analysis and and how do they help?
Yeah, so so these are just kind of tools
and approaches to you know, to analyze
the code and you know, understand
what it does and what potential defects
it might have. So, that looks at the
source code, the physical files. Well,
not physical, but
the text files for the word.
Yeah, so static code analysis, I mean,
it looks like a bit it looks a bit like
a compiler, right? So, so it it it it
builds your source code and builds
typically an abstract syntax tree. Uh
so, it creates a structure and then it
might build some additional graphs that
can be analyzed. And then you'll have a
series of rules where you'll say, you
know, I don't want to free a pointer and
then free a pointer a second time. And
so, you know, the the static analysis
will, you know, examine the graphs of
the source code, you know, the the
abstract syntax tree, and it will look
for, you know, different structural, you
know, various structural defects in the
code or potentially do some some path
analysis or some data flow analysis.
So, so static analysis tends to be very
good at finding, say, structural
problems in a program. It's not as good
at data flow and control flow type of of
things. No, that's the things that it's
caught me on is where
you return from a function cuz there's
an error, but you haven't freed what
you've allocated beforehand. And that
that's always something that I find on
my stuff.
Yeah, I mean, there there are some
problems that
are are fairly amenable to uh static
analysis. But but frequently,
you know,
memory management,
concurrency, these aren't always
discoverable through static analysis. So
so often, dynamic analysis is more
effective to find these type of
problems. And so, you you know, you do
have things
like address sanitizer,
thread sanitizer that available in clang
and and GCC and and and these let you
and and you know, variety of other
products, but these
allow you to instrument the executable.
And then, once it's instrumented, you'll
you'll exercise it using whatever
variety of of test you have available,
perhaps using fuzz fuzzers to to drive
the code with various inputs.
And these uh instrumented executables
now will be able to basically trap on
on, you know, any sort of any sort of
violation. So So So So they're very
dynamic analysis is more effective at
discovering
things like dynamic memory issues and
and concurrency issues.
Yeah, some of the stuff I mean,
basically runtime.
Some of the things that you've mentioned
in your book that I've played with and I
use in my projects is the
the sanitizer ones.
The TSAN, which is the thread one, the
ASAN, which you mentioned as well, the
address sanitizer for memory things.
And then the UBSAN, which is the
undefined behavior. And where I seem to
find errors using those is when I'm
running my test suite cuz I'm not as
careful as
when I'm actually running the
the core product, as it were.
I always find
issues where I've set up the test case,
but I haven't torn it down right or
something, you know, which which is kind
of a biggie and you should sort it out,
but at least it finds them. And then
some of the other tools that I see other
people use
is the the sanitizers, the clang
sanitizer one that you mentioned, and
then there's loads of I think it's
a lot you mentioned a few in your book.
But if you've got an open source
project, it's quite easy to get access
to all these free tools, but I think
most of them are commercial.
And I'll put some links into my show
notes for that.
Yeah, and and you know, I don't know
where to go with this. I mean it
it really you know, C is a is difficult
language. I mean
It's simple, but it's simply hard as
well, isn't
Yeah, simple. I'm not sure you know,
yeah, it's it's smaller than other
languages and so I guess from that
respect you could you could say it's
simple, but there there are, you know,
there's so many layers to it, you know,
that I'm still peeling after
since I started programming C in 1985,
so I'm still still peeling after And
what sort of things have you come up
with really recently that have surprised
you?
Oh, so here's a good one. This was
probably the most recent thing that
surprised me. So you can define an enum
and you can have a an enumeration
constant which has a type which is
different from the base type of the
enumeration type.
Yeah, cuz I thought enums were just
supposed to be
a thing that
meant something to you.
Yeah, well, there's there's this
question there's always this question of
you know, what is the type of these
things, right? So you you write enum
color red green blue, okay, so so what
normal example. Yeah, so what what type
are those things, right? So
so there's a strong tendency to well,
the standard will say, you know, that
the enumeration constants, the red green
blue, those should all be int. But, you
could say, for example, you could pass
your, you know, GCC or clang, you know,
flag which says use use short
enumeration constant. So, in a case like
that, red, green, blue, GCC or clang
might say, "Well, you know, I've only
got three values, 0, 1, 2. I can easily
fit that in an unsigned char. So, I'm
going to save quite a lot of storage and
and make this unsigned char. So, now
you've got the the base type of this
object is
unsigned char, but the type of each
enumeration constant is int.
So, and and mostly mostly you don't
notice this, but there are cases where
say you're doing generic programming and
you're trying to,
you know, execute some particular code
based on the type of something, it might
come as a surprise to people to discover
that the type of the constant is
different than the the type of the the
enum object, right? That's that's
somewhat surprising. Yeah, that's a good
one. Yeah, that's that's that's the one
that's got me most recently, but
you mentioned something there I thought.
What's the point of a signed char and an
unsigned char? Just cuz you mentioned
it. Yeah, well, signed char and unsigned
char are basically small integer types.
Okay. If you want to represent a
character, you you should use char,
plain char. And all three of those types
are
are different and incompatible types.
Perfect.
Okay, just before we start wrapping up
the show, just to put some more meat
into the tool section.
So, we've had a good, oh, sorry, a good
cover of static and dynamic analysis.
We've mentioned the T-San, A-San, and
Ubersan.
Ubisan, sorry. Um Ubersan, I like that.
Yeah, Ubisan. Um fuzzing, this is a good
one. But, over the this year we spoke
about Annex K. Is that something that we
can actually use today? It's been out
for a while. You mentioned it in your
book and Yens mentions it in his.
Yeah. Do you recommend it?
Yeah, I I like it. You know, there's
there are two schools of thought there
there
and and you know, we voted on this in
committee a couple times and the
committee's equally divided on this.
Half the committee hates it, half the
committee likes it, right? And because
it's in the standard, you can't you
can't eliminate it. You can't change the
standard without consensus, right? It's
the status quo unless, you know, you
can't add anything, you can't remove
anything without consensus.
And so,
you know, some of the history of this it
it was it started with Microsoft back in
the the '90s. You know, as a reaction to
some, you know, well-publicized
vulnerabilities.
And, you know, basically it it it sort
of improves upon the
the existing string library functions by
typically adding an additional argument
which specifies the size of destination
array, right? So, now when you call
these functions, they can determine
that, oh, you know, there's not enough
room in this destination array to make a
a copy of this string. And so, rather
than write beyond the bounds of the
object, I'm just going to, you know,
indicate an error either by invoking a
runtime constraint handler or returning
an an error value.
And so, I, you know, I like these. I
think they they improve they make it
easier for
novice programmers to avoid buffer
overflows, undefined behaviors.
Companies like Cisco have used these
extensively and have, you know, swear by
them. They they they they claim to have
had, you know, significant significant
improvement in quality and and security
is a a result of using these functions.
So, they're available, you know, clang
and GCC a lot of the a lot of vendors
sort of
don't like these libraries. That might
be might be because they originated from
Microsoft or could be other reasons.
But, there are there are third-party
versions these libraries that you can,
you know, download and and use and they
are they are, you know, standard
standard APIs. So, I
I like them. I would recommend their
use. Thank you. And now there to finish
off this section, there's standards that
we talk about. There's the CEREC E
Mhm. guidelines that Yeah, I remember
that.
E. Yeah, that's right.
And
I remember listening to a show
by SQL Lite how they spent a year
getting their C code up to some medical
standard. Can't remember what it was,
but I'll add it in.
Is that a thing? Is that something you
heard you've heard of? Some type of
medical
Medical standards. Some type of medical
standard where that code is suitable to
be deployed in medical equipment.
Well, I'll have to do some more research
for that, but Yeah.
Okay, so I think that was really good.
Let's start wrapping up. So, obviously C
is a very powerful language with a
strong history and deployment base.
But, if there was one thing a software
engineer should remember from our show,
what would what would you like that to
be?
If we haven't covered it or just
something you want to bring to the top.
Mhm.
Yeah, okay. I'll say this. Yeah, you
know, so we we didn't spend a lot of
time talking about IDEs, right? But, you
know, there's
an interesting thing people will say
about C programmers is that
C programmers
are a little frustrated by sort of
compiler diagnostics and they they want
to get past that
so they can get to the real job of of
debugging the program, right?
And there's there's
you know, there's one style of
programming which is this trial and
error, right? So, you you have a bit of
a problem, you you Google, you go to
Stack Overflow, you find a code example,
you copy paste that into your system,
you tweak it, you compile it, it doesn't
compile, there's some diagnostics,
oh, yeah, I misnamed this a variable,
misspelled, you make some mis- you know,
improvements, it compiles,
and then you run it and it it doesn't
quite run, so you change something and
now you get a run that succeeds and
you're like,
cool, that's working, onto the next
thing.
And and so this this this kind of
technique of trial and error, it can get
to a program which which works in a you
know, kind of a you know, optimal
scenario, right? But it doesn't mean
that program's correct, right? You don't
know how that program's going to deal
with, you know, kind of unexpected data.
And you know, we we talked about input
validation briefly, but really, you
know, your your code has to work with
all possible,
you know, data values, right? There
can't be
any inputs for which the program's going
to exhibit, you know, incorrect
behavior, right? So, so that's that's
the point of
you know,
input validation in in programming in
general, right? Make sure that you deal
with all all possible combinations of
data.
So, so to do this,
you know, trial and error's really
insufficient. You need to understand
um
you know, the language, you need to
understand the the code you're writing,
and you know, make sure you understand
all possible cases that you're
considering type conversions, you're
considering integer overflow and all
these Yeah, and I told
I switched to one. I used to just use
text editor, I think, and
whatever you use, there's loads of C
plugins and
the amount of time you save by
just looking at what's gets highlighted
or, you know, before you've even clicked
build or, you know, you run a make
command,
most of your problems are solved if you
just pay attention to the to the
Yeah, it it
it helps a lot, but it it's still is
still definitely inadequate because, you
know, all the all all the tooling isn't
going to find all the problems. So,
you know, it is it is helpful to
you you know
to understand the language you're using
and, you know, you could
you could achieve that through, you
know, training classes, you can achieve
that through through reading. What one
thing I did when I so transition from
being a programmer to a you know, secure
coder is I spent some time mostly in
Visual Studio and I would I'd write a
little bit of C source code and I would
sort of predict in my head, you know,
what sort of assembly would be generated
from that code and then I would compile
it and then I would be surprised, you
know, so I would go back and read the
standard, like, okay, now I understand.
And so
eventually I got to the point where I
could successfully predict, you know,
the assembly code that's being
generated. Until you until you get to
that point, your your your understanding
of the language is sort of falling
short, right? So
Yeah, there's something to be said for
just actually
experimenting and and
what I like to call it, you know, prove
proving it to yourself, basically, you
know. Right.
Have that assumption and and write a
test or something. Yeah, and and and you
you you know
what I do is I, you know, I kind of
perfect some code, right? Where I I gain
a lot of confidence. I understand this.
I know what this is. I I you know, I can
use this. And now I've got kind of
reusable component I can use. But, you
know, it's quite dangerous to sort of
just throw in a bunch of things because
they're there without, you know, really
understanding it yet. You know, so I
mean, maybe it's more more fun, but it
doesn't necessarily produce secure
systems.
So,
just to summarize before we we shut up
the
the podcast, what one thing would you
like them to to to remember is that
be good with your IDE, you know, pick a
good one or prove your assumptions, or
what would you like them to
remember out of that?
You know, I would say the you know, the
best time to
you know, avoid a defect is when you're
when you're coding, you know. So, it
it's better, you know, it's better to
write correct code initially than it is
to you know, try to find and repair
defects downstream. I mean,
correct coding, you know, quality code,
secure code, it's it's difficult to
achieve and you know, you you really
need to
use all the available tools and and
processes and and discipline to to, you
know,
to get close to achieving that. But,
yeah, the most important thing is sort
of
writing code securely to begin with.
Thank you. If people want to find out
more and
explore some of these things we've
talked about, where's the best place to
get in touch? You're pretty active on
Twitter.
Is that the best way?
Yeah, I can be found on Twitter. I have
a I have a website, robertseacord.com,
I think, where
I've got you know some errata for the
effective C book there's a
there's a link there
to update your SSL certificate cuz I was
looking at that last week
and it was complaining
Oh yeah
that it was insecure of all things
Yeah Okay so your Twitter account and
your Robert C
you could look there I'm on LinkedIn as
well so I'm
I'm not uh I'm not very hard to find I
don't have any handles anywhere I guess
I'm
Yeah it's all RCS on Twitter
for those that want to go there straight
away
Okay Robert thank you for coming on the
show it's been a real pleasure and this
is Gavin Henry for Software Engineering
Radio and thank you for listening
Thanks for listening to SE Radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine For more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at SE-Radio.net
To provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our Slack channel at SE-Radio.slack.com
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5
Thanks for listening